Finding Aid for Earle Wilbur Dow papers, 1885-1945
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Earle Wilbur Dow papers 1885-1945
Dow, Earle Wilbur, 1868-1946.
851294 Aa 2
Professor of history at University of Michigan. Correspondence and miscellanea concerning the University and personal affairs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
5 linear feet
The collection was the gift of Philip Dow (donor no. 4562 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Earle Wilbur Dow was born April 28, 1868 in Bellefontaine, Ohio. He graduated from the University of Michigan in 1891, then taught school for a year in Manistee, Michigan. He returned to the U-M in 1892 as an instructor of history. From 1894 until 1898, he studied abroad at Leipzig University and the University of Paris. He returned to the University of Michigan in 1899 as assistant professor of European history. He became full professor in 1902. He was the author of An Atlas of European History. He retired in 1938 and died January 8, 1946.
The Earle W. Dow collection consists mainly of correspondence with other historians and University of Michigan colleagues. Appended to this finding aid is a selective index to Dow's correspondents. Beyond correspondence, there is a scattering of other material relating to Dow's University of Michigan activities and to his involvement with the Belvedere Club of Charlevoix, Michigan.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Dow, Earle Wilbur, 1868-1946.; University of Michigan. Dept. of History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Schools--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Visual Materials: Contributor
Gibson's Photographic Gallery (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Contributors:
Adams, Herbert Baxter, 1850-1901.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Blacker, Robert R., b. 1845.; Bourne, Henry Eldridge, 1862-1946.; Clowry, Robert Charles, 1838-1925.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Dixon, Frank Haigh, 1869-1944; Effinger, John Robert, 1869-1933.; Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943.; Gale, Esson M. (Esson McDowell), 1884-1964; Gresham, Walter Quintin, 1832-1895.; Hampton, Charles S., 1856-1917.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.; Jameson, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1859-1937.; McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.; Markley, Joseph Lybrand, 1859-1930.; Pattengill, Henry Romaine, 1852-1918.; Reighard, Jacob, 1861-1942; Salmon, Lucy Maynard, 1853-1927.; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.; Wahr, George, b. 1861.; Ward, Henry Baldwin, 1865-1945.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1885-1899, 29 folders (Box 1)
  - 1900-1904, 22 folders (Box 2)
  - 1905-1912, 33 folders (Box 3)
  - 1913-1945, 22 folders (Box 4)
- Other papers
  - 1901-1930, 17 folders (Box 4)
  - 1932 (Box 5)
  - 1935-1936 (Box 5)
- University of Michigan
  - General 1886-1911 (Box 5)
  - General 1912-1913 (Box 5)
  - Michigan Schoolmasters' Club (Box 5)
- Investments
  - Stock market 1911-1927 (Box 5)
  - E.B. Cadwell and Company Market Letter 1907-1912, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Hayden, Stone and Company Weekly Market Letter 1914-1915, 2 folders (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous
  - Belvedere Club of Charlevoix, Michigan 1924-1938 (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea 1898-1945 (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 9 folders (Box 5)
  - Photograph: of students in the chapel of Ann Arbor High School, taken by Gibson Photo, Ann Arbor, Michigan. (Box 5)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adams, Herbert Baxter, 1850-1901.
Nov. 9, 1894
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.
Apr. 20, 1900, May 21, 1902
Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.
Oct. 7, 1904, Dec. 21, 1904
Blacker, Robert R., b. 1845.
Oct. 6, 1892
Bourne, Henry Eldridge, 1862-1946.
Jan. 19, 1904
Clowry, Robert Charles, 1838-1925.
Aug. 5, 1904
Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.
July 1895
Dixon, Frank Haigh, 1869-
Jan. 11, 1904, Apr. 1898, Sept. 1898
Effinger, John R. (John Robert), 1869-1933.
Aug. 1913
Ely, Richard Theodore, 1854-1943.
Oct. 1900, Nov. 1900
Gale, Esson McDowell, 1884-
Jan. 30, 1914, June 23, 1914, Nov. 3, 1914, June 1927
Gresham, Walter Quintin, 1832-1895.
May 26, 1894
Hampton, Charles S., 1856-1917.
June 16, 1890
Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.
June 6, 1902
Jameson, J. Franklin (John Franklin), 1859-1937.
Oct. 1904
McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.
Jan. 1904, Apr. 1904, July 1904, Oct. 1904, 1917, 1927
Markley, Joseph Lybrand, 1859-1930.
June 14, 1902, Aug. 9, 1904
Pattengill, Henry Romaine, 1852-1918.
May 25, 1892, May 28, 1895
Pattengill, Henry Romaine, 1852-1918.
Apr. 27, 1917
Salmon, Lucy Maynard, 1853-1927.
Jan. 7, 1913
Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.
July 9, 1904
Wahr, George, b. 1861.
June 12, 1898
Ward, Henry Baldwin, 1865-1945.
Apr. 5, 1894, May 28, 1895